Guide to the French Revolution and Napoleonic Period Manuscripts, 1752-1882 (bulk 1788-1815)
French Revolution and Napoleonic Period Manuscripts, 1752-1882 (bulk 1788-1815)
- Autograph manuscripts
  - France-Go (Box 7)
    - Genlis, Stéphanie de, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 7, Folder 51)
      AL in French: part of a letter, with translation
    - Georges-Weymer, Marguerite, a.k.a. "Mademoiselle Georges", to another lady, n.d.; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 7, Folder 52)
      AL in French, plus tanslation and two portraits of the actress
    - Gérard, Comte Francois, to Colonel Drouot, 14 Sept. 1839; 2 leaves + 1 leaf (Box 7, Folder 53)
      ALS in French, plus a portrait of Gérard
    - Gérard, Baron Francois [= the painter], to ?, 1829; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 7, Folder 54)
      AL in French, plus a portrait of Gérard
    - Gillet, People's representative to the Army of Sambre-et-Meuse, to Gen. Schérer, 7 oct. 1795; 1 leaf +2 leaves (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Girodet-Trioson, to Fellow-Painter Marie-Nicolas Ponce-Camus, 14 Jan. 1813; 2 leaves + 1 leaf (Box 7, Folder 56)
      ALS in French: invitation to come and see one [out of twelve] full-length portrait of Napoleon in imperial costume in his atelier
    - Gironvillle, to the Minister of War, 1 Dec.1800; 1 leaf (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Goblet, Francois, to Senator Lemercier, 20 oct. 1808; 1 leaf (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Gohier, Louis-Jérôme, to ?, 22 aug. 1797; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Gohier, Louis-Jérôme, to the Minister of war, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Gohier, Louis-Jérôme, to Mr. Villenave, 10 Sept. 1828; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Gosse, and twelve other Republicans from Bricquebec, to the Minister of War, 1794; 1 leaf (Box 7, Folder 62)
      ALS in French, containg interesting information about Bricquebec (Manche) and the civil war: "a band of Chouans and brigands has invaded our Department, where they have brought terror by assassinations, fire and pillaging... We beg you, Citizen, to send us arms and ammunitions..."
    - Gouges, Olympe de, to Mr. [de la Ferté?], 27 Oct. 1788; 1 leaf (Box 7, Folder 63)
      ALS in French [part?], about the rejection by the Comédie française of one of her plays, "Molière chez Ninon, ou le Siècle des grands hommes"
    - Gourgaud, Baron, to Colonel Boilleau, 1831, 1834; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 7, Folder 64)
      ALS in French, plus another letter from Boilleau, and portraits of Gourgaud
    - Gouvion Saint-Cyr, Laurent de, 10 Sept. 1817; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 7, Folder 65)
      ALS in French, plus an administrative document signed by the same, plus portraits
  - Gr-Laf (Box 8)
    - Grangeneuve, Jean Antoine, to his wife, 30 March 1792; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Gratien, General Pierre, 13 July 1794; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Grégoire, Abbé Henri, to Mrs. Barlow, 16 July 1803; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 3)
      ALS in French, with translation: mentions Joel Barlow and Robert Fulton
    - Grégoire, Abbé Henri, to Mme Dauriat, 17 May 1820; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 4)
      ALS in French, plus translation: "The decent deputies of the Left congratulate me for having been declared unworthy by the scoundrels [who] wish to bring France back under the yoke of oligarchy."
    - Grenier, General Paul, to the Minister of War, 21 Nov. 1812; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Grobert, Commissaire des guerres, to the Administrators of Cremona, 1800; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Grouchy, Marquis Emmanuel de, 3 March 1837; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 7)
      ALS in French, plus a second letter, plus translation, and a portrait
    - Guizot, François Pierre Guillaume, to an Autograph Collector, 10 May 1860; 1 leaf + 5 leaves (Box 8, Folder 8)
      ALS in French, plus portraits of Guizot and his wife Eliza
    - Haugues, Victor, and Lebas, French Commissionners to the Iles-du-Vent (French Polynesia), 1795; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 9)
      ALS in French, plus translation: laissez-passer for an American citizen
    - Hanriot, François, 15 May 1794; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 10)
      ALS in French: military certificate for Citizen Graindorge, sealed
    - Harcourt, François-Henri, duc d', n.d. [between 1778 and 1789]; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 8, Folder 11)
      ALS in French, plus translation: military status of Dumouriez
    - Hastrel, Adjudant General, 1800; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Hédouville, General Gabriel d', to ?, 30 oct. 1797; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 13)
      ALS in French, asking for info about Hoche, plus translation and portrait
    - Hédouville, General Gabriel d', French Ambassador to Russia, to Jean-Baptiste Gail, Professor of ancient Greek at the Collège de France, 12 July 1803; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Heisen, Wilhelm, 29 May 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 15)
      ALS in French: military report, with translation
    - Henrion, François, to the French Senators, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 16)
      ALS in French; endorsement by Ducos
    - Hérault de Séchelles, Marie-Jean, et alii, to the Committee on Legislation, 18 Dec. 1792; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 17)
      ALS in French, about the Dpt. of Montblanc, also signed by Grégoire, Jagot and Simond
    - Hérault de Séchelles, Marie-Jean, to the Attorney-General of the Dpt. of Meurthe, 19 oct. 1793; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 18)
      ALS in French, about his family estate at Marainville
    - Herman, Armand, to Auguste Neveu, 11 april 1794; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Hesine, Pierre-Nicolas, to Emile [Babeuf], 20 March 1807; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Hesine, Pierre-Nicolas, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 21)
      portrait of Gracchus Babeuf accompanied by a poem gloryfying him
    - Hoche, Lazare, to the Chef de Bataillon Barré, 6 April 1796; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 22)
      ALS in French, with the mention "Deeds, not Words", translation, and four portraits
    - Hoche, Lazare, to the Commission intermédiaire [?], 1797; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Hoche, Lazare, to General paillard, 1794; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Hohenloe-Bartenstein, Prince von, to the Minister of War, 17 Oct. 1819; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 25)
      ALS in French: about foreign desertors, and their willingness to join the regiment raised by Hohenloe, plus a portrait
    - Hortense [de Beauharnais], former Queen of Holland, Duchesse de Saint-Leu, 23 Oct. 1814; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 8, Folder 26)
      ALS in French, and portraits
    - Houchard, General, to the Minister of War, 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Huard, Genealogist, 1796; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 28)
      Document in French: list of documents given to the Archives Départementales de la Seine
    - Hubert-Dumanoir, Jean Michel, to Citizen Lemit, 13 June 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Hugo, Victor, to Etienne Carjat, n.d.[1860s?]; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 8, Folder 30)
      ALS in French (draft?), about an article for "Le Boulevard", with translation. Also, COPY of a famous letter to Garibaldi (1868), whose original is in Rome, Italy, Museo Centrale del Risorgimento, Archivio Garibaldi, vol. 242 nr.36 (2), plus portraits of Hugo and Garibaldi
    - Huin, Joseph, to the "Citoyens Ministres", 2 Jan. 1793; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 31)
      ALS in French, endorsed by Jacques-Louis David
    - Hulin, General, to the Commander of Milan, 28 July 1800; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Isabey, Jean-Baptiste, to M. Carbonel, Directeur de la Musique de la Reine Hortense, 21 May 1812; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Jérôme Bonaparte, future King of Westphalia, 11 March 1807; 1 leaf + 5 leaves (Box 8, Folder 34)
      ALS in French, regarding the exchange of a naval officer; plus five portraits
    - Jérôme Bonaparte, former King of Westphalia, to Lady Augusta Holland, 20 febr. 1854; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Joachim [Murat], King of Naples and Sicily, to General Nansouty, 15 July 1812; 1 leaf + 9 leaves (Box 8, Folder 36)
      ALS in French, signed "J. Napoleon", plus translation, and portraits of Murat
    - Joseph Bonaparte, 5 Jan. 1839; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 5 leaves (Box 8, Folder 37)
      ALS in French, from Point Breeze in Bordentown, New Jersey, USA; plus a second letter (1805), and portraits
    - Joubert, General, to the Minister of War [Bernadotte], 7 Aug. 1799; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - Jourdan, Jean-Baptiste, French Administrator of Piemonte (Italy), to Lemarquant, 22 May 1801; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Jourdan, Jean-Baptiste, French Administrator of Piemonte (Italy), to Petiet, 30 July 1801; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Junot, General, to General Thiebault, 23 oct. 1803; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - Kellerman, Marshall François-Christophe, to the People's Representatives to the Army of the Alps, [1793]+ 8.Nov. 1806; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 4 leaves (Box 8, Folder 42)
      ALS in French, plus a second letter to the Minister of War, annotated and signed by Dejean; protests a misleading title given to him in an official letter: "Si pareille chose était arrivée dans mes bureaux vis-à-vis de vous, j'aurais déjà chassé à coups de pieds dans le cul le drôle qui se serait permis une telle impertinence." Dejean: "C'est une erreur que M. le Maréchal prend pour une insulte."
    - Kellerman, Marshall François-Christophe, to the People's Representatives to the Army of the Alps, 1821; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Kilmaine, General, to ?, n.d.; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 8, Folder 44)
      ALS in French, and notes
    - Kléber, General Jean-Baptiste, to General Grenier, 10 Jan. 1797; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - Labadie, Commissaire-Ordonnateur, to the Payeur-Général de l'Armée de la Moselle, 1. Nov. 1794; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - La Barrollière, General, to Barbé-Marbois, 19 July 1803; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Laborde, de, to ?, 18 Jan. 1812; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - La Bouchère to M. Largeleau, in Libourne*, 2 dec. 1778; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 48b)
      ALS in French: "Il vient d'arriver un navire de Boston, ou il est parti le 3 novembre. Mr. le comte d'Estaing y était encore avec son escadre... On témoigne quelques craintes pour nos possessions d'Amérique. Le commerce n'avait pas besoin de nouveaux désastres, il est déja assez maltraité."
    - Laborde, Colonel de [acting in the name of Louis-Napoléon Bonaparte], to ?, 6 Sept. 1848; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Lacépède, Comte Bernard de, to General Lamarque, 20 May 1807; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 8, Folder 50a)
      ALS in French, plus a second letter to Pluvinal (July 1807), plus a portrait, and a notice
    - Lacépède, Comte Bernard de, to Monsieur Sourreil, chevalier de la Légion d'honneur, 20 May 1807; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 8, Folder 50b)
    - Lacombe du Tarn, Jean Pierre, to Daurière, 8 Oct. 1794; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - Ladmirault, General, to "Le Moniteur Universel", 6 dec. 1813; 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - Laffite, Jacques, to Mr. Poingestre, in London, 23 May 1818; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Lag-Ler (Box 9)
    - Lagau, Philippe [Consul Général en Basse-Saxe, based in Hamburg], to Williams, American Consul in Hamburg, 13 June 1797; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Lagrange, Commissaire-Ordonnateur in Luxemburg, to Séttiveaux, 27 May 1795; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Lallemand, to Haller, Administrateur des Finances et des Contributions d'Italie, 10 April 1797; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Lally-Tollendal, Gérard-Trophime de, 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 4)
      ALS in French: note on his birth and baptism
    - Lally-Tollendal, Gérard-Trophime de, 30 July 1793; 1 leaf + 2 leaves + 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Copies of ALS in French, plus translations and portraits
    - Laloy, 25 Aug. 1797; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Laloy [Commissaire du Directoire en Haute-Marne] to the Minister of Finance, 28 Aug. 1798; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Lamarque, General, to general Ernout, 4 Aug. 1798; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Lamartine, Alphonse de, to ?, 2 Sept. 1852; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 9)
      ALS in French, plus portrait
    - Lameth, Alexandre de, to M. Etienne Michel, 30 Jan. 1806; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Lameth, charles Malo François de, to a Deputy?, 28 Jan, 1791; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Lanjuinais, Comte Jean Denis de, to Van Praët, Conservateur de la Bibliothèque Impériale, 23 Febr. 1810; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Laplace, Pierre-Simon de, to Marshall Kellermann, 10 Oct. 1805; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 9, Folder 13)
      ALS in French, on the administration of the District or Sénatorerie of Colmar, and the Senator's official accomodation plus translation and portraits
    - La Revellière-Lépeaux, to ?, n.d.; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 14)
      ALS in French, plus translation; plus a second document, brevet de lieutenant, bearing the signatures of La Revellière-Lépeaux, Lagarde, and Petiet; plus a portrait
    - Lariboisière, Comte Jean, to the Minsiter of War, 13 Aug. 1811; 1 leaf + 6 leaves (Box 9, Folder 15)
      ALS in French, endorsed by Marshall Suchet, plus translation and notes
    - La Rochefoucault-Liancourt, to Frochon, Préfet de la Seine, 13 June 1797; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 16)
      ALS in French, on his radiation from the list of emigrés, plus translation
    - Larrey, Dominique Jean, to Dr. Cugnot, Surgeon-General, 13 June 1797; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Lasalle, General, 16 Jan. 1809; 1 leaf + 4 leaves (Box 9, Folder 18)
      ALS in French (report), countersigned by Generals Guilleminot and Fririon, and by Daru, plus portraits
    - Las Cases [the elder], to Capitaine Baudin, 20 July 1827; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Las Cases [the younger], to Dr. Millet, 1844; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Lasteyrie, Charles de, to ?, 6 July 1804; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Latouche-Tréville, Admiral Louis de, to General Leclerc, 11 Oct. 1802; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 22)
      ALS in French, plus translation, countersigned by Leclerc
    - La Tour du Pin de Gouvernet, Jean de, 6 Nov. 1789; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 23)
      ALS in French: certificate
    - Latour-Maubourg, Marie Victor de, 11 Febr. 1809; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Latour-Maubourg, Marie Victor de, 29 April 1820; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Launay, Bernard René Jourdan, Marquis de, 13 June 1797; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 9, Folder 26)
      ALS in French: the Marquis and his wife née Le Boursier, "living in Paris at the Chateau de la Bastille, parish of Saint-Paul" agree to pay to Mr. Sauvage 1,000 livres anually; plus translation
    - Lautal, General, to the Minister of War, 1800; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Lavalette, Directeur des Postes, to Prince Louis Bonaparte, 11 Oct. 1805; 1 leaf + 4 leaves (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Lavalette, Mme Louise de, to ?, n.d.; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 9, Folder 1)
      ALS in French. plus portraits
    - Laville-Leroux, 13 June 1797; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Leblond [Conseil de conservation des objets de sciences et d'art], to the Bureau du Domaine National, 13 April 1796; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 31)
      ALS in French: seizure of the artworks kept at the house of a family of émigrés (hôtel de Fleury, rue Notre-Dame des Champs), and of the library of a seminar (Saint-Nicolas du Chardonnet)
    - Lebon, Joseph, 26 Dec. 1793; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 32)
      ALS in French: annotation on the minutes of a meeting in St. Pol
    - Lebon, Veuve Silvestre, to the Duc d'Angoulême, 18 Oct. 1820; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Lebrun, Charles-François, to the Minister of Finance*, 11 September 1822; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Lebrun, Charles-François, Duc de Plaisance to ??, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Lebrun-Tondu, Pierre Henri, to Citizen Drouas, 18 Oct. 1792; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Lebrun-Tondu, Pierre Henri, to Captain Paul, 21 Febr. 1793; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 9, Folder 36)
      ALS in French, registering a vote of the thanks expressed by the Convention to an American captain for having saved the passengers and the crew of the French ship "La Belle Créole"; plus notes on Lebrun-Tondu
    - Leclerc de Juigné, Mgr Antoine, 1784; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 37)
      ALS in French: Fonfdation de voeux faits pour le Dauphin
    - Lefebvre, General, to ?, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Lefebvre, General, to Réal, 6 Nov. 1799; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Lefebvre, General, to the Minsiter of Finance, 6 Nov. 1799; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - Lefevre-Gineau, Louis, to ?, 4 Aug. 1813; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 41)
    - Lefort, Commissaire des Guerres, to Dubois-Crancé, 18 Oct. 1792; 1 leaf + 8 leaves (Box 9, Folder 42)
      ALS in French, endorsed by Genearl Moreau, plus portraits of Moreau
    - Le Graverend, Jean-Marie, to ?, 20 June 1814; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - Le Graverend, Jean-Marie, to Béranger, Conseiller d'Etat, 20 June 1814; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - Le Graverend, Jean-Marie, to M. Laderer, 7 Febr. 1815; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - Le Graverend, Jean-Marie, to ?, 5 June 1817; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 46)
    - Le Graverend, Jean-Marie, to ?, 7 July 1824; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 47)
    - Le Pelletier, Commissaire des Guerres, to M. Cauchy, 7 Aug. 1807; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - Le Ray de Chaumont, James, 7 Aug. 1807; 1 leaf + 9 leaves (Box 9, Folder 49)
      [New York] ALS in French, plus notes
    - Lerouge, to the Citoyens Administrateurs de la Monnaie, 22 April 1796; 1 leaf (Box 9, Folder 50)
  - Les-Mol (Box 10)
    - Lespinasse, People's Representative in The Nord, to Noël-Gabriel-Luce Villar, 1. Jan.1796; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 1)
      ALS in French: endorsement of a candidate to the Institut de France
    - Lespinasse, General, to the Cdt. de l'Artillerie, 17 Jan. 1798; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Les..., Baron de [Major in the Royal-Suedois], 14 June 1752; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 3)
      ALS in French, on the medical discharge of Heinrich Zimmerman, endorsed by the Duc de Broglie, with translation
    - Loison, General, to General Berthier, 23 Dec. 1803; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Louis XV, King of France, 12 March 1771; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 5)
      [Port de l'Orient, or Lorient, Brittany]
      ALS in French: mandate to arrest and put in jail "a fugitive Negro slave belonging to lord Rivalz de St. Antoine, member of Council of the Isle of France [Mauritius]"
    - Louis XVI, King of France, 1. March 1775; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 6)
      ALS in French: assignation of Mr. De Cussac in Le Grand-Morne, Saint-Domingue, to fulfill the duties of "Capitaine Aide-Major des Milices"
    - Louis XVI, King of France [?], n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 7)
      ALS in French: short note to the King's valet de chambre, Chamilly
    - Louis XVI, King of France, 31 July 1788; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Documents in French [COPY]: "Réponse du Roi a MM. les députés des Etats de Bretagne"
    - Louis XVI, King of France, n.d. [1793?]; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 9)
      ALS in Italian, entitled "Testamento di Luigi XVI, scritto da lui... il giorno 21. Gennaio 1793", plus a note by Prof. Mario Einaudi (Cornell)
    - Louis XVIII, King of France, 15 Oct. 1814; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 10, Folder 10)
      ALS in French: attribution of the Ordre de Saint-Louis to Antoine Hardouineau de Guineux, plus portraits of the king
    - Louis Bonaparte, King of Holland, to the Minister of Finance, 16 April 1805; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 10, Folder 11)
      ALS in French, plus translation, and portraits
    - Louis-Philippe I, King of the French, to M. de Salvandy, 3 July 1834; 1 leaf + 12 leaves (Box 10, Folder 12)
      ALS in French: order to attend the opening of the Parliament, co-signed by Adolphe Thiers, pl;su portraits of both men
    - Luckner, Nicolas de, 9 Sept. 1791; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 13)
      ALS in French: leave of absence
    - MacDonald, General, to the Minsiter of War, 27 Oct. 1798; 1 leaf + 5 leaves (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - MacDonald, General, 1800; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 15)
      ALS in French: satisfecit delivered to Cdt Lefort
    - Magallon, General, to local administrators, 11 Nov. 1794; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Maison, General, to the Minister of War, 1804-1814; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Maison, General, to ?, 1811; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Maison, General, to the Minister of War, 1814; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Malartic, Amable [French Governor of Mauritius], n.d. [1794]; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 20)
      ALS in French: military order
    - Malesherbes, Chrétien-Guillaume Lamoignon de, n.d. [after 1776?]; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 21)
      ALS in French, documenting his activity as a botanist
    - Malesherbes, Chrétien-Guillaume Lamoignon de [?], to ?, 26 Nov. 1775; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 21)
      ALS in French [authentic?], documenting his membership in the Académie française
    - Malesherbes, Chrétien-Guillaume Lamoignon de, to M. Abeille, n.d. [ 1775?]; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 22)
      ALS in French [authentic?], on pensions
    - Malet, François, to the Minsiter of War, 1799; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Malleville, François Jacques de, to Barbé-Marbois, 14 July 1812; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Mallarmé, François, to the People's representatives to the Army of Pyrénées-Orientales, January 1794; 1 leaf + 2 leaves + 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 25)
      ALS in French, plus translation, and a biographical note
    - Mallet du Pan, Jacques, 25 June 1784; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - Malouet, Pierre Victor, to an Admiral, n.d. [before 1806]; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Manuel, Pierre Louis, to the Procureur Syndic du Dpt de la Seine, 8 Nov. 1792; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Manuel, Pierre Louis, 26 Aug. 1792; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Marbot, General, to ?, 1824; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Marchand, Louis-Joseph-Narcisse, former valet de chambre of Napoleon, to ?, 22 April 1796; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 31)
      ALS in French: service record of Gen. Brayer
    - Mareschali, to Caillard, 9 april 1802; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Maret, duc de Bassano, to the Minister of Finance*, 5 Jan. 1807; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 33a)
      ALS in French, on the sale of houses by Marshall Kellermann
    - Maret, duc de Bassano, to Duroc, duc de Frioul, Grand Maréchal du Palais, 6 July 1810; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 33b)
      ALS in French, following the grand ball given by Prince Schwartzenberg at the Austrian embassy to celebrate the marriage of Napoleon and the Austrian archduchess Marie-Louise(on 1 July, 1810): "S.M. m'a ordonné d'informer Votre Excellence de l'intention ou Elle est de n'assister désormais à aucune fête, réunion ou assemblée que les lieux n'aient été visités par son architecte."
    - Maret, duc de Bassano, to the Minister of Finance, 27 April 1812; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 34)
      ALS in French, on the capture by French pirates of an American boat, "The Herald"
    - Margueritte, and other citizens, 22 April 1796; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 35)
      ALS in French: deposition concerning officers' behavior on the 10th of August, 1792, during the attack of the Tuileries
    - Marie-Antoinette, Queen of France, 1 July 1774; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 36)
      ALS in French, with seal (broken): nomination of a dignitary [Ecuyer de la Bouche de la Reine]A
    - Marie-Louise, Impératrice des Français, 3 May 1812; 1 leaf + 8 leaves (Box 10, Folder 37)
      LS in French, on the newly founded Société de la Charité Maternelle, plus portraits
    - Marmont, Auguste, 19 Jan. 1815; 1 leaf (Box 10, Folder 38)
      ALS in French: accepts the title of Honorary Commissioner of the Association of the Chevaliers de Saint-Louis; plus portraits